hello today i have a very interesting
report for you
it affected multiple websites because
the bug was in django framework
and it allowed bypassing csrf protection
this bug was reported on hacker one by
sergey bovrov back in 2014
to fully understand this vulnerability
you need to know something about google
analytics
and first thing you need to know is that
it's meant to track
users activity and to do it it uses
cookies and in the cookie
there is a field for referrer host and
referral path
and they are put into the cookie
unfiltered
and in the attack scenario where the
attacker tricks the victim into visiting
attacker.com website and then he
redirects the victim into the vulnerable
side with google analytics
the attacker's com website and path
will be visible in the victim's cookie
so in such attack scenario
the attacker completely controls the
victim's cookie
and the hunter mentioned that he had
reported this behavior to google
and was rewarded for it so he actually
got two bounties for this report
one from django and one from google
so now it's time to understand how do
web servers
handle cookies and actually it's a very
simple text processing mechanism
the cookies are being sent in the cookie
header
in the form of name equals value
semicolon
another cookie name equals another quick
value and so on and so on
and turns out that a lot of web servers
also accept
columns instead of semicolons as the
cookie separators
but what python plus django did was also
accept
square brackets and this was the
behavior that browsers
completely did not expect and this is
the vulnerability here
because if there was a square bracket in
the cookie value
the browser did not think that it might
be interpreted
as a cookie separator so the browser
would not encode it
nor filter it nor anything it would just
send it as the cookie value
and the web server would actually
interpret the same input
as the two separate cookies
so now we can chain these two things by
injecting a square bracket
into the path of our website and then
when the victim will open a link of the
vulnerable site
our square bracket will be put into
google analytics cookie
and the browser will send this cookie
thinking it just a standard
cookie value but the django web server
would understand this
as two separate cookies but there is one
more thing
actually at the end of the cookie there
are attributes and the attributes may be
like domain and path which are very
important
and as the attacker we want to override
them somehow
but we can't just erase them but happens
out that browsers
only take into consideration first few
attributes and the rest is ignored
so what we can do is just put our
attributes
as the first ones and put many of them
it might be the same attribute over and
over again it doesn't make
any difference and what the browser will
do
is just consider those first attributes
and
ignore the last ones which will be the
actual ones
appended by google analytics
so now we have a way to set an arbitrary
cookie for the victim with arbitrary
attributes
and now you may be thinking how can we
actually exploit this
to bypass csrf protection
so there are multiple approaches to csrf
prevention
and one of them is double submit cookie
mechanism
it works this way that it sets a cookie
called for example csrf token
and then when the form is sent the same
value
has to be in the request body
what the server does is it just
validates whether the same value is in
the body and in the cookie
it's very efficient for the server
because it does not have to store
anything in the database it just
compares the value from the cookie
with the value from the body and why
does this work
because as the attacker you can
obviously set an
arbitrary value in the request body of
the csrf you're trying to make
but you don't control the cookie value
and you have no way of doing this
unless you have a way to set an
arbitrary cookie
and that's exactly the way that this
attack works
we have a way to set a cookie for the
victim so you set
a csrf token cookie for the value that
you want
and then you send the same value in the
body the server
just compares whether two values are the
same
and they are so the request goes through
there's also a little bit of luck
involved
because the actual csrf token cookie
sent by the server will be sent in your
request
but if the web server sees two cookies
with the same name
it will take the latter value so it
might be
a little bit random but generally it
works
so that's it for today's report i think
those ones that affect
frameworks are especially interesting
because they might mean
that half of the internet is vulnerable
in this very example it was not the case
because the site had to use django along
with google analytics
and double submit cookies so this
limited the amount of sites vulnerable
but i still think that it's a very very
interesting report
the fix was of course not treating
characters like square brackets as
cookie delimiters
by django so thanks for watching this
video
if you've learned something new leave a
like and a subscription
and for now good bye